Okay, now that we have seen how to do
registry naming and how to follow the
true dependencies and so on, we we are
ready to learn what the instruction
level parallelism or ILP is. So we will
now define what it is. So the ILP really
can be defined as this IPC instructions
per cycle when we have a processor that
can do an entire instruction in one
cycle. So it doesn't need a pipeline. It
can fetch, decode, execute, write
result, everything in just a single
cycle for one instruction. Also, the
processor can do any number of
instructions in the same cycle. So
theoretically, it could just fetch and
execute your entire program in the one
cycle, but it still has to obey true
dependencies. So if one instruction
depends on another, then they cannot be
done in the same cycle. You have to
first do one and then the one that needs
its result. So as you can see ILP really
is kind of what an ideal processor can
do subject only to obeying true
dependencies. How do we compute the ILP
for a program? Well, we first rename all
the registers. So we do register
renaming first and
then we pretend we execute. So what we
do is we say okay in the first cycle
these are the instructions that don't
depend on anything so they can go. So in
the next cycle we go through the same
thing and so on until we run out of
instructions to do at which point we
know how many cycles it is. Now the one
thing that you should remember about the
ILP and that will help you realize what
it is and how to do it is that ILP is a
property of a program not of any
particular processor. So basically we
define the LP to be what would this
program do as far as the IPC is
concerned on an ideal processor. So it
has nothing to do with what kind of
processor you actually run it on. It has
everything to do with just the
dependencies in the program. So be
mindful of that because for example it
doesn't make really sense to say
something like what's the ILP on this
program on the I don't know Intel Core
i7 processor because the ILP on the
Intel Core i7 processor is beside the
point because the LP is really the
performance of this program on an ideal
processor that has nothing to do with
Intel i7. Okay. So just just remember
that when you're asked to produce the
LP, you should just consider the
program. It doesn't matter what the
processor looks like because the LP is
computed for a perfect processor anyway.
In contrast, you could say that the IPC
of this program on a given processor is
something else. But be mindful of this.
Basically, the LP you only need to see
the program. You don't really need to
know what the processor looks like.